So today's דף *daf* is מ"ז *mem-zayin*, but we pick up in
the middle of מ"ז *mem-zayin* עמוד ב' *amud bet*. בעזרת השם *B'ezrat
Hashem* and we are in the middle of talking about
stages of development of boys and girls.
Yesterday we was at a משנה mishna, *mishna* that well first it
sort of wrapped up the questions about in this פרק perek. *perek*
called מופלא סמוך לאיש *Mufla Smuch l'Ish* if you make a vow
then to what degree is that vow really binding and binding for
you, binding for others and so on. But then the next משנה
mishna *mishna* talks about the very important question about the stage of
development for a young girl because a girl has two stages. 12
and a day with two pubic hairs is a נערה Na'arah *naarah*,
and then when she gets to the next stage of of you
know
physical development of puberty she's a בוגרת Bogeres. *bogeret*. And the משנה
Mishnah *mishna* actually went in great detail describing what exactly the physical
signs of that stage were. Interestingly other גמרות *Gemaras* say that it's
really you don't need to look at physical signs. It's really just
a straight six months from the time that the two pubic hairs
come after 12 years and a day. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
and the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* went to great detail talking about the
exact issue of the physical signs and how that is relevant or
not we will see later today in the beginning of the next
פרק perek, *perek*. But let's take a look now at the last
משנה Mishnah *mishna* of this פרק perek *perek* which talks about for
a boy and for a girl what happens if they are not
developing normally in terms of their physical development. So the משנה Mishnah.
*mishna* says the following: בת עשרים שנה Bas esrim shana, שלא הביאה
שתי שערות *bat esrim shana shelo hevia shte searot*, if you have
a woman 20 years old who still doesn't have two pubic hairs,
so the absence of two pubic hairs even if she's now 20
years old this is actually quite fascinating because normally you assume okay
fine it's measured by physical development but still it's roughly around the
same time as a certain type of an intellectual maturity. Well let's
say you have somebody that's not developing physically, they could have been
like you know in terms of their in terms of their intelligence
and maturity, emotional maturity, they're 20 years old but you know halachically
it's somewhat interesting they're still considered to be a minor because they
lack the stages of physical development. So you have a young woman
who's 20 years old who does not have her pubic hairs and
halachically she's a minor. So what is תביא ראיה שהיא בת bas
עשרים שנה והיא אילונית *tavi raya she'hi bat esrim shana v'hi aylonit*?
And if he can prove that she's now 20 years old and
20 years old without pubic hairs you are now considered an אילונית
*aylonit*. And אילונית *aylonit* is actually, I don't know, I'm sure it's
a Greek word I forgot, I didn't look it up, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does an etymology that has to do with like
איל *ayal*, like almost like a ram like she is somehow has
some like male characteristics to her. She's certainly not developing as a
female, we're going to see the flip by a boy. And therefore
לא חולצת ולא מתייבמת Lo Chaltzah V'lo Misjabemes. *lo choletzet v'lo mityabemet*.
So therefore she is considered to be a what an adult. Which
is not explicit in the משנה Mishnah *mishna* but is implicit elsewhere
is that this person is a קטנה *ktana* and we'll see similarly
by a boy a קטן katon *katan*, until it's clear that they're
not going to develop physically. And if they're not going to develop
physically and they've reached a certain age then already they're considered to
be an adult but a sterile adult because they have not had
a period of puberty. And therefore because she's an adult she therefore
well she can't do ייבום *yibum* or חליצה Chalitzah *chalitza*. She doesn't
have to do ייבום *yibum* or חליצה Chalitzah *chalitza*. That really all
focuses on the fact that we say that she's not able to
have kids. If she's 20 years old and doesn't have physical signs
of development and clearly she's not going to be able to have
kids, if she's not able to have kids then there's no מצווה
*mitzvah* of חליצה Chalitzah *chalitza* or ייבום *yibum* with her because, but
she now can be married. What's not explicit in the משנה Mishnah
*mishna* is the משנה Mishnah *mishna* could be read that it's just
focusing on the fact that she is no, is not fertile, is
not you know and is assumed to be sterile. And since she's
assumed to be sterile there's no מצווה *mitzvah* of חליצה Chalitzah *chalitza*
or ייבום *yibum* with her, her husband dies and now she can
marry whoever she wants next. That's all the משנה Mishnah *mishna* saying.
But elsewhere what we find out is that at this stage also
is when she's considered an adult because the absence of pubic hair
was making her considered a minor until this point. Similarly בן ben
עשרים שנה שלא הביא שתי שערות *ben esrim shana shelo hevi shte
searot*, a man 20 years old, a young man who has not
brought two pubic hairs, so יביא ראיה שהוא בן עשרים שנה והוא
סריס vehu saris, *yavi raya she'hu ben esrim shana v'hu saris*, once
he can prove he's 20 שנה *shana* and then he is, and
here the word is a clear what it means, סריס saris. *saris*
where it is a eunuch, he is a he is sterile essentially
לא lo, חולץ ולא מייבם *lo choletz v'lo meyabem*. And therefore if
his if his brother died he there's no מצווה *mitzvah* of חליצה
Chalitzah *chalitza* or ייבום *yibum* with him. It's not necessary. The sister-in-law
can go ahead and get remarried because the מצווה *mitzvah* of ייבום
*yibum* was only if the woman could have kids and if the
brother-in-law is able to provide her with kids. Okay so again in
the משנה mishna *mishna* all that's clear is that they're considered to
be sterile. It's not clear that this is when do they become
an adult. That's sort of elsewhere particularly in יבמות Yevamos *Yevamot* and
elsewhere but anyway here the emphasis is that at this stage we
know that they're going to be sterile and therefore it has implications
for the מצווה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibum*.
What if somebody is sterile and they do and they are physically
mature and they're still sterile?
Right so I mean then there also would not be if that
yes yes there would still be no מצווה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibum*.
In terms oh you mean if somebody got married and then it
was proven they were sterile would that be a מקח טעות *mekach
taut*? Would it be like the marriage would be annulled? So You
know so that's discussed in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in כתובות *Ketubot*
about a woman who's discovered to be an אילונית *ailonit* as it
emphasizes primarily about the woman
and I'm trying to remember and I'm thinking that it might be
a debate I'm thinking it might be a debate of רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*. I'm trying to remember but there definitely
is an aspect of תוספות *Tosafot*. The question is whether it's just
תוספות *Tosafot* to the extent that there's no כתובה *ketubah* that you
assume that nobody would have that the man wouldn't have
obligated himself for כתובה *ketubah* in those circumstances or whether it's actually
the entire קידושין *kiddushin* is בטל *batel*. But yes there definitely is
an element of תוספות *Tosafot*. I'm not remembering offhand how extensive that
is.
If the
man, right, right, because I know
there's a very well-known case, right, right, so
they forced him to give a גט *get* but did they annul
the marriage?
No he kept on until unfortunately the woman who started out young
was past childbearing age and then because of some pressure on him
after his mother died, somebody told a true story, somebody told him
a friend of his mother's told him that his mother came crying
to her in a dream saying she can't get into גן עדן
*Gan Eden* because her son is withholding a גט *get* so he
gave the גט *get*.
But he had been you know medically
sterile and still had that right, right.
Nobody
annulled the marriage, right, right.
So I I have to check. I know that it's an explicit
point in in כתובות *Ketubot* about the woman and I'm trying to
remember whether it's about the whether it's about the marriage is annulled
or whether it's just relating to the כתובה *ketubah*. And about him
then yeah then that I don't think that that's as explicit but
yeah, right, right.
Yeah
so there definitely are yeah yeah there definitely are implications but whether
they're as extensive as
annulling the marriage that that I'd have to check. Apparently from this
case certainly that wasn't how that court ruled. So yes so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay so here it's saying that he's sterile.
It doesn't say explicitly whether he's an adult or not. And תוספות
*Tosafot* points out anyway we basically rule that יבום yibum? *yibum* can
be effective by a minor. So the emphasis here is not whether
adult or minor. The emphasis here is that they are considered to
be sterile. The
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אלו דברי בית הלל
Beis Hillel *eilu divrei Beit Hillel*. Those are the words of בית
הלל Hillel. *Beit Hillel*. והוא סריס saris, לא חולץ ולא מייבם *v'hu
saris lo choletz v'lo meyabem* of what I remember of that. אלו
דברי בית הלל *eilu divrei Beit Hillel*. Those are the words of
בית הלל *Beit Hillel*. בית שמאי Beis Shammai אומרים זה וזה בן
שמונה עשרה *Beit Shammai omrim zeh v'zeh ben shmoneh esrei*. No boys
or girls when we say they reach this age that they're defined
to be sterile if they have no signs of puberty, they don't
have to be twenty, eighteen is sufficient. רבי אליעזר אומר הזכר כדברי
בית הלל והנקבה כדברי בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Rabbi Eliezer omer hazachar
k'divrei Beit Hillel v'hanekeivah k'divrei Beit Shammai*. The male goes by twenty,
the female by eighteen. כי אשה ממהרת לבוא לפני האיש *ki ishah
mimaheret lavo lifnei ha'ish*. A woman becomes physically mature before the male
and the same way you have the twelve, thirteen difference under normal
circumstances, here it would be eighteen, twenty to say if they're not
you know haven't developed at this stage then already they could be
determined that they will not reach an age or they will never
sort of develop physically. There must be a condition like this. I'm
not sure. If Charlie was here she could tell us what the
medical condition is. So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. ורמינהי *u'reminhu* asked on this
said the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אחד בן תשע שנים ויום אחד v'yom
echad, ואחד בן עשרים שלא הביא שתי שערות *echad ben tesha shanim
v'yom echad v'echad ben esrim shelo hevi shtei sa'arot*. There's the same
הלכה halacha. *halacha* for a nine-year-old and a day. Remember a nine-year-old
and a day is assumed to be able to have an act
of sex but is not an adult. And that is the same
הלכה halacha *halacha* as a twenty-year-old that does not have two pubic
hairs. Which means what? Which means that it is considered an act
of sex but he's not considered an adult. So here הלכה halacha
*halacha* here by the way you get the what's not clear at
all in the משנה mishna *Mishnah* that until this age he is
not you know no matter even though he is nineteen and three
quarters whatever he's not an adult because he does not have this
physical development. So why is this a question? Now the relevance of
that means that if they do an act of יבום yibum. *yibum*
as we know a nine-year-old and a day does an act of
יבום yibum. *yibum* basically it's binding but not a hundred percent and
if they want to sever you need a גט *get* and מיאון
*miun* the verbal severing and the same is somebody who is twenty
and hasn't brought two hairs. It's an act of sex at this
stage same way a nine-year-old and a nine-year-old with or without two
hairs, I think I said with, doesn't matter, a nine-year-old with or
without two hairs is still an act of sex but it's not
yet an adult so same is this person that is twenty years
old. So now we have a problem. This said twenty years old,
our משנה mishna *Mishnah* says once it's twenty years old then he's
already an adult. And if we're talking in the context of יבום
yibum *yibum* if that was the sense of this ברייתא baraita *braita*
which it was because it was from יבמות *Yevamot* then that means
that it should not be a יבום yibum *yibum* at all once
they hit twenty years old then he's a סריס saris. *saris* there's
no act of יבום yibum *yibum*. And this ברייתא Beraisa *braita* suggests
that just like the minor it is binding as an act of
יבום yibum *yibum* because it is an act of sex. So clearly
this ברייתא Beraita: *braita* assumes that twenty years old is still not
considered a סריס saris *saris* and it's still not considered an adult.
So what do you do with this? So אמר רב Rav שמואל
Shmuel בר רב Rav, יצחק אמר רב Rav *amar Rav Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak amar Rav* והוא שנולדו בו סימני סריס *v'hu shenoldu bo
simanei saris*. There are two stages. If you're twenty and don't have
the physical development and you have physical signs of being a סריס
*saris*. סריס, of being sterile, and the גמרא Gemara in יבמות details
what that is. Here רש"י Rashi has, רש"י Rashi says some of
it, like it has
something to do with like your sweat glands, you know how you
sweat,
or your, you know, the rest of the hair on the rest
of your body, or your skin is very smooth. There are other
types of lack of, like, these, you know, signs of any lack
of development that would be associated with puberty. So if you have
associated indicators, then you are considered to be sterile at the age
of twenty and then already you go to being an adult. Whereas
if you, all you're lacking at this stage is the pubic hairs,
then we don't seal the identity at the age of twenty, we
give you further before we define halakhically that you're considered to be
sterile. So גמרא Gemara says how old is that? So the first
גמרא Gemara says like this, דיקא נמי, Deeka Nami, אמר רב אדא
דיקא נמי, Amar Rav Adda Deeka Nami, that's also inferred from the
words of the משנה, mishna דקתני והוא סריס, deqtani vehu saris,
it says the משנה mishna says if you're twenty then you are
the והוא סריס, you are a סריס. It didn't just say the
הלכה. halacha It's interesting, so that somehow means like there's evidence for
that or somehow they're reading that, although it's not clear, that that
indicates that there's other supporting evidence. שמע מינה, Shema mina, that's a
good point. וכי לא נולדו לו סימני סריס עד כמה? Vechi lo
noldu lo simanei saris ad kama? And if a person does not
have these indicators, when would he finally be considered to be sterile
and what goes with that is an adult? So תני רבי חייא
עד רוב שנותיו, tani Rabbi Chiya ad rov shnosav, until a majority
of his years. What's the majority of his years? So it assumes
here based on the פסוק pasuk in תהלים, Tehillim, right? ימי שנותינו
שבעים שנה ואם בגבורות שמונים שנה, Yemei shnoseinu shivim shana ve'im bigvuros
shemonim shana, right? So that assumes that that means 70, so
35. When a guy hits 35, he enters his 36th year. Then
if he has, if he has no pubic hairs, but no other
signs of being a סריס, only then is he considered a סריס.
So again, what's the emphasis here is whether it's considered to be
a, you know, a binding act, whether it's considered to be potentially
if he's still fertile and he's in an act of sex. But
elsewhere what's not explicit in this גמרא Gemara but what I'm telling
you is, and this is I think this is a much bigger
חידוש, chidush, is that as long as he doesn't have the pubic
hairs, he will continue to have a status as a minor. He
could be 20 years old, he could be 34 years old and
be a minor because he does not have that physical development. And
it's only once we're prepared to say the reason of the lack
of physical development is that he is sterile or she is sterile,
then we can consider this person to be an adult. So only
at the age of twenty with additional evidence or at the age
of thirty-five without additional evidence where we say we identify them as
sterile and that they are considered an adult. But before that they're
still considered a minor. So this person who's twenty years old, what?
They can't do יבום? yibum
No, they're considered halakhically to be a
minor. Yeah. Yeah, it's not
just that's my point, it's not just for the laws of יבום.
yibum, They really are considered to be a minor, which is, again,
that's not you would not have known that from this גמרא Gemara
but it's based on others.
So less than that, you know, when they're still in this stage
of being a minor or whatever or not being considered, then you
see the act, I mean the evidence is a little indicated from
the ברייתא braita that we quoted, although you could have said maybe
that's only for laws of יבום. yibum But that when he doesn't
have pubic hairs he could be you know twenty or whatever and
he does this act of יבום Yibum, and it's not yet a
full act of יבום Yibum. because he's not fully married to her
yet, that says it's just like as if a minor had done
that act. So it's true, you could have said well maybe for
acts of יבום Yibum. he's not yet considered because that's related to
sex, maybe there he's not yet considered to be fully an adult.
But the actual הלכה halacha is that he's considered to be really
a minor and that the need for physical maturity as part of
the halakhic definition of adulthood. And it's contracts and everything?
Yeah, I mean again
I'm trying to think if like I know that you know evidence
where it's actually been paskened in like you know like in a
real case, but that's certainly the way it is in the codes,
that that he's halakhically a minor. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, so where are we? כי אתו לקמיה
דרבי חייא, Ki asu lakamei de'Rabbi Chiya, so when they came to
רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya,
what would he do if somebody had somebody that didn't have pubic
hairs? So he says, אי כחיש איהו בנסי i kachish ihyu binsei
אמר להו אברוייה. amar lehu avruyei. You know, fatten them up, get
them healthy. אי ברי, i bari, if he was healthy, אמר להו
אחשוה. amar lehu achshusha. You know what, like sort of get him,
you know, maybe take him off some of the good food. Why?
דהני סימנים זמנין דאתו מחמת כחישותא זמנין דאתו מחמת בריאותא. de'hanei simanim
zimnin de'asu machmas kachishusa zimnin de'asu machmas bri'usa.
Sometimes these pubic hairs they come as a result of being sort
of a little bit underfed and sometimes they come as a result
of being very healthy or a little bit like overfed or fed
well. And therefore he wanted to first try to medically treat it
to the degree that they were able before having to give a
ruling as to this person's status. אמר רבא הלכתא בכולה פירקא מעת
לעת, Amar Rava hilchasa bechola pirka me'eis le'eis, the law in this
entire chapter is goes from מעת לעת. me'eis le'eis. Now normally what
מעת לעת me'eis le'eis means is it's talking about when we're measuring
things in days. And the question is do we measure them in
full halakhic days or do we measure them in 24 hour units?
So for example when we say a ברית מילה, bris milah, we
don't say it's מעת לעת, me'eis le'eis, we say it's the eighth
day from the ברית, bris, you know to be the first second
of the day or if we need to be in the morning,
and even if the kid's born I don't know at six, you
know like. 6 PM if it's before שקיעה shkiah you can have
the ברית מילה bris milah you know in the morning. You don't
need to wait a full eight 24-hour days. That's normally what how
we contrast מעת לעת me-es l'es as opposed to halachic days. Here,
and normally it's almost always halachic days or a few exceptions, like
there might be an issue for example about what do you call
it about פדיון הבן pidyon haben or something like that. Anyway here
we're not talking about that because here we're talking about years. So
the issue about מעת לעת me-es l'es is not an issue about
can you do go by hours or do you go by full
days, it's actually a question of do you need to enter into
like the beginning of the next year. You'll remember we had some
discussion before like let's say the person is it's not the day
of their בר מצוה bar mitzvah it's the day they were born
on I don't know ז' אדר Zayin Adar and now it's the
next year and it's like ו' אדר. Vav Adar. So we say
they have to get not only be the last day of their
13th year but enter the 14th year, the one day later. Okay,
as opposed to that's what we're saying here this phrase of מעת
לעת me-es l'es means, that's at least the way רש"י Rashi, understands
it seems pretty clear from the גמרא Gemara you know that you
have to enter into the next period of time and it's not
going and it's not sort of just into the day before. So
according to רש"י, Rashi one minute, let me just look at רש"י
Rashi
let me just double check this one minute.
No, no, I'm sorry I'm sorry, according to רש"י Rashi it's a
bigger difference. The point is like this. You're entering into let's say,
this also gets to a discussion we had earlier. You're entering into
your 13th year, right, your בר מצוה, bar mitzvah, when when are
you considered בר מצוה bar mitzvah when you actually begin your 14th
year. So רש"י Rashi says that the issue here is and again
it's a funny phrase to use מעת לעת me-es l'es because this
is not normally the way it's used is that don't think it's
enough to enter your 13th year, be 12 years and a day,
that would be considered you have to actually do a full 13
years, so מעת לעת me-es l'es here is emphasizing a full 13
years and you have to actually begin your 14th and be 13
and a day. Okay, so that's really the difference here. Normally מעת
לעת me-es l'es is is more well it depends on the context
but anyway often it could be more time, the idea of מעת
לעת me-es l'es they're going by halachic days. Like the example I
gave you by the ברית מילה bris milah is if somebody is
born you know Sunday towards the end of the day, right, you
could still do the ברית מילה bris milah right on the morning
of Sunday. That's not מעת לעת. me-es l'es. מעת לעת me-es l'es
meaning it's full, it means you have to go actually toward back
you know
מעת לעת me-es l'es is a fuller counting. You would have to
go all the way till the time he was born. So here
when we say מעת לעת me-es l'es means if somebody was born
on whatever ז' אדר Zayin Adar was the example I gave it's
not enough to sort of start the year. If you think about
starting the year it's like starting the day by the ברית מילה.
bris milah. So by ברית מילה bris milah you can start the
beginning of Sunday and have the ברית. bris. Here it's not enough
to start the 13th year, no, you have to do the entire
thing and you have to actually enter into the 14th. So it's
a little unusual phrase to use מעת לעת me-es l'es but that's
how רש"י Rashi understands what's going on.
Is this a different concept than מקצת היום ככולו? miktzas hayom k'kulo?
Right, so מקצת היום ככולו miktzas hayom k'kulo assumes that you're counting
sort of the normal units and then right a little bit counts
as a מקצת היום. miktzas hayom. So it is a little bit
related, it's true. Which is also why I hesitated to say that
מעת לעת me-es l'es is always longer because if you don't say
מקצת היום ככולו miktzas hayom k'kulo then you could somehow say that
without doing מעת לעת me-es l'es it's longer because you don't have
the partial previous days and it would need to go, right. So
it's not always a question about longer or shorter, yes. So
and also if you were actually to tell me מעת לעת me-es
l'es and I would be thinking that we're talking in terms of
hours so I would say if the guy was born ז' אדר
Zayin Adar at 6 AM or whatever at 1 PM you have
to wait till the next you know you have to wait till
1 PM after anyway but that's not what it means here. Here
it basically means you don't begin the year, you have to go
till into the next year. בכולה פירקא מעת לעת. B'chula pirka me-es
l'es. You go from time to time, meaning that you have to
go into the following year. ועולא אמר תנן תנן Ve'Ula amar tnan
tnan
where it says in the משנה mishna. that's true, which is most
of the משניות mishnayos it said ויום אחד, 12 years and a
day, this year so and today. דלא תנן לא תנן D'lo tnan
lo tnan where it didn't say it's not true. Where did it
not say? Our משנה. mishna Our משנה mishna said 20 years and
doesn't have pubic hairs. So it didn't say 20 years and a
day, it said 20 years. So it doesn't mean a full 20
years, it doesn't mean מעת לעת. me-es l'es. So what does it
mean? So the גמרא Gemara is going to say maybe it means
just entering the 20th year, right, that's an ambiguity in our משנה.
mishnah It says 20 years and not having two pubic hairs, maybe
it means in your 20th year. So that's what it looks like
yes, that's what our משנה mishnah. means. So בשלמא לעולא היינו דקתני
הכא יום אחד והכא לא קתני. Bishlama l'Ula hainu d'katni hacha yom
echad v'hacha lo katni.
So according to Ula it makes sense all the previous משניות mishnayos
bothered to say 12 and a day, 13 and a day, 3
and a day, 9 and a day, and here it didn't say
and a day to tell you as long as you're into the
20th year. אלא לרב לישתני Ela l'Rav lishtani but according to Rav
why didn't it say here 20 and a day? ותו תני רבי
יוסי בן כיפר אומר משום רבי אליעזר Vesu tani Rabbi Yossi ben
Kipar omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer we taught in the ברייתא braita Rabbi
Yossi ben Kipar says in the name of Rabbi Eliezer שנת עשרים
שיצאו ממנו שלשים יום הרי היא כשנת עשרים לכל דבריו shenas esrim
she-yatzu mimenu shloshim yom harei hi k'shenas esrim l'chol devarav
the 20th year which is significant here for a person that does
not have pubic hairs, once 30 days went out of it it's
like the 20th year for all purposes. וכן היה רבי בלוד V'chen
hayah Rebbe b'Lod and Rebbe taught the same way in Lod שנת
שמונה עשרה. shenas shmoneh esreh.
The 18th year that 30 days have gone out of it—let's go
get back to that phrase in a minute—הרי היא כשנת שמונה עשרה
לכל דבריה harei hi kishnat shmoneh esre l'chol devara counts as the
18th year. So בשלמא bishlama דרבי deRebbi דרבי יוסי בן כיפר deRabbi
Yosei ben Kifar לא קשיא. lo kashya. So first you'd say, well,
why does one say 20, one say 18? So okay, that we
know the answer to, because we saw in the משנה mishnah there
was a debate of 20 and 18. הך כבית שמאי הך כבית
הלל. hach keBeis Shammai hach keBeis Hillel. That בית שמאי Shammai says
18, בית הלל says 20. So fine, 18 and 20 is not
going to bother us. But they both agree you don't need to
get into the 21st year, into the 19th year, they just say
30 days.
How do we get these years anyway, 18 and 20?
All right, that's all מסורה. mesorah. אלא לרב קשיא, Ella leRav kashya,
but according to רב Rav, it's difficult, because according to רב, Rav
if you say that, meaning so basically,
so here you see, what does he say? Why does it work?
If you say you don't need a full amount, so you don't
need a full amount, so we could debate how much into the
20th year? Maybe a day into the 20th year, maybe a month.
I should say, tell you that the normal assumption is when they
say יצאו ממנה שלשים יום yatze'u mimena shloshim yom means
you've already been 30 days into your 20th year, 30 days into
your 18th year, which makes sense, and that's normally the assumption, like
30 days in a year counts as a year. So if one
day counts as a month, 30 days counts as a year, it's
sort of like the next smallest unit. So a year is made
up of months. So maybe 30 days into the 20th year counts
as a full 20th year. The רמב"ם Rambam reads it differently. The
רמב"ם Rambam reads שיתצאו ממנה sheyatze'u mimena means it's lacking 30 days.
That you're 20 years and 11 months, or 18 years,
you're one month away from finishing your 20th year, you're one month
away from finishing your 18th year. But either way, the point is,
look, there's a, if you say you don't need a full year,
you don't need to enter your 21st, enter your 19th, then we
can discuss a day, a month, according to the רמב"ם Rambam 11
months, but we're saying it doesn't have to be a full 20th
year, a full 18th year. And that's why the משנה mishnah didn't
say יום אחד yom echad because somewhere when you're in your 20th
year, that makes sense. אלא לרב קשיא. Ella leRav kashya. רב Rav
says it has to be into your 21st year. So how come
we have this idea of a month and so on? How does
that work? So the גמרא Gemara says, and how come our משנה
Mishna doesn't say יום אחד? yom echad? So the גמרא Gemara? says
תנאי היא, tanna'ei hi, you're right, it's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim,
דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braisa שנה האמורה בקדשים, shana
ha'amura b'kadshim, שנה האמורה בבתי ערי חומה. shana ha'amura b'vatei arei choma.
Where it says a year by קרבנות, korbanos, by sacrifices, that an
animal is kosher only when it's like one year old, two years
old, and so on. Or when it says the year by when
you sell a house in a walled city, that if you don't
buy it back within a year, you lose your right to buy
it back. או שתי שנים שבשדה אחוזה, o shtei shanim shebisdeh achuza,
or two years for a field of inheritance, that you have after
two years, you're entitled to buy it back, but not prior to
two years. שש שנים שבעבד עברי, shesh shanim shebe'eved Ivri, or that
you own a Hebrew slave for six years and he goes free
in the seventh. וכן שבבן וכן שבבת, vechein shebaben vechein shebabas, and
similarly by sons and daughters, which is the most ambiguous phrase here,
which we're going to analyze. כולן מעת לעת. kulam me'et le'et.
They all go by 24 hours, they go by from time to
time. Now again, time to time as contrasted to what? I would
have said it's contrasted to like not going by ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. You know, not going by the calendar time, but going by
the actual year, and that's what it seems measured from, a year
from the event itself, not the New Year in terms of the
new calendar year. That also seems to be a possible contrast, and
that seems to be the emphasis here. So let's take a look.
בקדשים מנלן? bekadshim minalan? And how do you know it by sacrifices?
אמר אבא בר יעקב, Amar Abba bar Yaakov, אמר קרא, amar kra,
the פסוק pasuk says כבש בן שנתו, kevess ben shnato, a lamb
within its first year. שנתו שלו, shnato shelo, its first year, ולא
שנה שמניין העולם, velo shana sheminyan ha'olam,
not the year of the way people count, meaning of the calendars.
Meaning it doesn't matter that it was born before ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah and now it's after ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. You don't say
it's in its second year because it's after ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
You go by its birthday, you don't go by the calendar.
And that's the context here of מעת לעת. me'et le'et. The גמרא
Gemara says, right, but that's not about how old is the מעשר,
ma'aser, that's what year was it grown in. שנה האמורה בבתי ערי
חומה מנלן? Shana ha'amura b'vatei arei choma minalan?
How do you know about buying back your house in a walled
city that only within a year? אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק
pasuk says עד תום שנת ממכרו. ad tom shnat mimkaro. When the
end of the year of its sale. ממכרו שלו, mimkaro shelo, you
go by the year of the sale. You don't go by the
calendar year, oh we hit ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah you can't buy
it back. No, we go by its year. ולא שנה שמניין עולם,
velo shana sheminyan olam, not by the calendar year. שתי שנים שבשדה
אחוזה מנלן? Shtei shanim shebisdeh achuza minalan? How do you know about
a field of inheritance that after, you're only entitled to buy back
after two years? אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says ובמספר
שני תבואות ימכר לך. ubemispar shnei tvu'ot yimkar lach.
He shall sell it to you according to the years of the
grain, he shall sell it to you, which means that you get
at least two years of it before you're able to buy it
back. So the דרשה drasha is, if it already says שני, shnei,
the years, why does it have to say תבואות tvu'ot of grains,
which is seen as extra? פעמים שאדם מוכר שלש תבואות בשש שנים,
pe'amim she'adam mocher shalosh tvu'ot beshesh shanim,
because sometimes he can get three grain harvests out of two years.
If you sold it to him when the grain was standing and
ready to be harvested, and you waited two full years, it's possible
he would have harvested three cycles of grain out of two years.
Now what does that prove? It doesn't really prove, it's not exactly
clear how that proves you don't go by calendar, except if you
went... Maybe you measure it by grain years, by number of harvests.
So to say, you know, that's also an all possibility, right? Why
don't
we measure
the two years by grain years, by number of harvests that you
had? No, you don't go by harvests, you don't go by calendar,
you go by meaning the the normal, you know, ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, you go by two full years from the time of sale.
שש שנים שנה שבעבד עברי מנלן, shesh shanim shana shebeeved ivri minalan,
how do you know about a Hebrew slave that six years not
marked by you enter the seventh calendar year, but it's seventh year
from the birthday of from you know from the date of the
purchase? How do you know that? אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק
pasuk says, שש שנים יעבד ובשביעית. shesh shanim yaavod uvashviit. So
seven six years he shall work and on the seventh he shall
go free. So the דרשה drasha is six years he shall work
and on the seventh, ובשביעית נמי יעבד. uvashviit nami yaavod. He'll also
work on the seventh. Why? Because it's the seventh calendrical year, right?
Because you're into the seventh year you've had you know there's been
already you know the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah has hit again, so
you're in the seventh year on the calendar, but it's still six
years from the time he was purchased. So here by the way
the contrast is better why we're saying מעת לעת. meet leet. מעת
לעת meet leet means and that's normally the more use of מעת
לעת meet leet is that you go by the moment of the
event and not by some formal counting. So like I said you
go a ברית bris you don't go מעת לעת, meet leet, you
don't wait till 6:00 PM, you go by the halakhic day. So
here the same point is, you don't go by the calendar like
you do by a ברית bris the next year according to the
calendar, you go by the year measured from the event. Okay, so
here the contrast to מעת לעת meet leet is to the calendar
year. That wasn't exactly the contrast by being twelve or thirteen or
twenty, because we were never suggesting there that it was the calendar
year. But anyway, that's at least that's at least what's being said
here. Now we have to look at the last phrase. שבבן שבבת
למאי הלכתא? shebeven shebebat lemai hilkheta?
What does it mean that also by sons and daughters you go
by the full מעת לעת? meet leet? So אמר רב גידל אמר
רב, amar Rav Gidel amar Rav, so רב גידל Rav Gidel said
in the name of רב, Rav לענין ערכין, leinyan arakhin, when somebody
takes a vow, remember an ערך, erekh, to pay the value of
somebody, the ערך, erekh, and you go by the chart that's in
the תורה, Torah, so you say how old is he? Is he
five, is he six, you know, based on the chart, so you
don't go by a calendrical year, you go by whether by this
person's the year of the child him or herself. Now רשי Rashi
also says there as well that, you know, here because we're talking
about the age of the person, רשי Rashi then makes it similar
to the previous discussion in fact to say you don't go by
a calendrical year, it's also saying when he's in his fifth year
he's not considered to be five, right? That's the same point as
before. The contrast here by the age of the children is that
do we say that you have to be in your sixth year
you're five when you enter your sixth year or do we say
you're five in your in your sixth year? So here saying by
ערכין, arakhin, no, מעת לעת meet leet you have to enter into
your sixth year be five and a day to be five. Okay,
in your fifth year you're still not considered five and that's exactly
similar to the discussion earlier. ורב יוסף אמר veRav Yosef amar לפרקין
דיוצא דופן. lepirkin deYotze Dofen. No, for the chapters of יוצא דופן,
Yotze Dofen, the name of our פרק. perek So you see by
the way that this discussion was not held just in the context
of our פרק, perek it was more like a portable discussion, you
know. So therefore it was being explicit not to our פרק perek
but the פרק perek of יוצא דופן, Yotze Dofen, it's being placed
though the discussion here. So for all of these ages if you're
it has to be מעת לעת meet leet meaning you have to
be thirteen and a day, twelve and a day, twenty and a
day, you have to be into the twenty-first year being in the
twentieth year is not enough. And that's what רב Rav. says. רב
Rav says look you proved to me that this משנה Mishna didn't
say and a day, there was an idea that thirty days into
it counts, you don't need a full year. No, I have a
ברייתא braisa that says מעת לעת meet leet for sons and daughters
and I say what that means is it means for all of
these laws of this פרק perek it has to be מעת לעת
meet leet you have to actually enter into the next year. It's
not enough to be in the twentieth year. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye
said to them, מי פליגתו? mi paligtu? Do you guys argue with
one another? Meaning one says that מעת לעת meet leet is about
ערכין, arakhin, the other says it's about this פרק perek. of יוצא
דופן. Yotze Dofen. Are you disagreeing? Like you don't agree to what
the other one said? So
אמרו ליה, amru lei, they said to him, לא, הוא אמר חדא
ואנא אמינא חדא ולא פליגנא. hu amar hada veana amina hada velo
paligna. Or רב Rav said only to one of them I guess.
Anyway, I guess he said to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, not exactly
clear who he said to. Anyway, he says no, he says one
and I say the other and we don't argue. Okay? We both
agree with one another. Different ways of interpreting that ברייתא braisa but
we don't really argue. והכי נמי מסתברא, vehakhi nami mistavra, actually it
makes sense that we're not arguing. דאי סלקא דעתך פליגי, deei salka
daitakh paligi,
so if we really do argue, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
I say it applies to יוצא דופן Yotze Dofen and רב גידל
אמר רב Rav Gidel amar Rav says it doesn't says it applies
to ערכין arakhin if he didn't say it applies to יוצא דופן,
Yotze Dofen, מאן דאמר לערכין למה לי יוצא דופן? man deamar learakhin
lama lei Yotze Dofen?
So then רב גידל אמר רב Rav Gidel amar Rav who said
it applies to ערכין arakhin would say it's not true by יוצא
דופן, Yotze Dofen, you don't need מעת לעת? meet leet? That can't
be. The whole thing was brought to support רב. Rav, ואמר רב,
veamar Rav, רב Rav, himself said, הלכתא. hilkheta.
The entire פרק perek of יוצא דופן yotzei dofen including the ages
of 20 and 18 according to בית שמאי go מעת לעת. me'es
l'es. אלא, Ella, okay,
so meaning what did we say? Meaning remember that basically the one
משנה Mishna doesn't say יום אחד, yom echad, our משנה Mishna about
20 and not having two hairs. So does it mean in the
20th year or does it mean 20 and a day you're in
your 21st year? So רב Rav says it's just like all other
משניות, mishnayos, it means 20 and a day. What do you do
with the fact that we have it didn't say in a day
and the fact that we have a משנה Mishna, that says a
month into your 20th year and you don't need to be into
your 21st year? So he says I got this whole other ברייתא
braisa that says מעת לעת me'es l'es by sons and daughters. So
okay, but there's a problem because רב גידל Rav Giddal said in
the same in the name of רב, Rav the same רב, that
this ברייתא braisa we're talking about ערכין. Erchin. So it doesn't help
you. You're trying to say that this ברייתא braisa is talking about
בן ובת, ben v'bas, but we have a statement that you said
was talking about ערכין. Erchin. So the גמרא Gemara... says no no
no, רב says it could be talking about either ערכין Erchin or
about this פרק perek and therefore either way the ברייתא braisa supports
him. So the one who says ערכין Erchin is not denying the
read of the ברייתא braisa. or the הלכה halacha of the age
of 20 and vice versa. So now the גמרא Gemara, says אלא
מאן דאמר לערכין מאי טעמא לא אמר ליוצא דופן? Ella man d'amar
l'Erchin mai taama lo amar l'Yotzei Dofen? So if you're going to
say this ברייתא braisa. of going into the next year applies to
ערכין, Erchin, why didn't you say that if you say agree the
same הלכה halacha is by our chapter of יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen,
why didn't you read the ברייתא braisa that way? דומי דהנך, Dumi
d'hanach, no, because it's similar to the other things mentioned in the
ברייתא. מה הנך דכתיבי אף הני נמי דכתיבי. Mah hanach d'chsivin af
hani nami d'chsivin. The other things are all פסוקים psukim in the
תורה, Torah, right, about how old the קרבן korban and buying back
the fields and buying back the houses and the slave. So something
in the תורה. Torah. What's in the תורה? Torah? It's about ערכין,
Erchin, about the about when you say somebody is five years old,
less than five years old, more than five years old. That's a
פרשה parsha in the תורה, Torah, so I assume we're dealing here
with interpreting פרשיות parshios in the תורה Torah what age we're talking
about. The issue about being a סריס and age of majority, like
Michael said, it's not none of that is explicit in the תורה.
Torah. So that's not being discussed in this ברייתא. אף הני נמי
דכתיבי, Af hani nami d'chsivin, here too it's written. ואידך, V'idach, what
would the response
back be? השתא בבן ובבת, Haishtah b'ben u'v'vas,
if it was true that it was talking about ערכין Erchin it
shouldn't say sons and
daughters. שבזכר ושבנקבה מיבעי ליה, She'be'zachar v'she'benekeiva mibaei lei, right, because males
and females is the term used in the תורה Torah by ערכין.
Erchin. Sons and daughters is the phrase used in this entire פרק.
perek. בת עשרים שנה, בן שלש עשרה שנה, ben shlosh esrei shana,
בן this, בת that.
The phrase in this entire פרק perek. is בן ובת. ben v'bas.
So okay. אמר רב יצחק בר נחמני, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Nachmani,
so now so so okay so now we have a debate. We've
got the fact that our משנה Mishnah didn't say יום אחד. yom
echad. So there's one opinion that says even into the 20th year,
maybe a day, maybe a month, according to the רמב"ם Rambam 11
months, but you don't need to be in the 21st year. And
רב says no, it's also into the 21st year although it doesn't
sound it from the משנה. He's got a ברייתא that there's a
debate how to interpret but in principle everybody agrees you have to
be into a day into the next year in order for it
to count. Okay. אמר רב יצחק בר נחמני אמר רב אלעזר הלכה
כרבי יוסי בן כיפר שאמר משום רב אלעזר. Amar Rav Yitzchak bar
Nachmani amar Rav Elazar halacha k'Rabbi Yose ben Kippar she'amar mishum Rav
Elazar. And the הלכה halacha. is like like like רבי יוסי בן
כיפר Rabbi Yose ben Kippar that says in the name of רב
אלעזר. Rav Elazar. What does רבי יוסי בן כיפר Rabbi Yose ben
Kippar say? He said 30 days counts. Now again, the simple read
of that is 30 days into the 20th year. The רמב"ם Rambam
means it when
you're saying it to mean that when you're 30 days before the
end of the 20th year, 11 months into it. But the simple
read is once you're one month into the 20th year and if
you're lacking these signs of puberty, you're lacking the pubic hairs, then
your הלכה halacha status changes. So he says we rule that way.
Okay. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, רב זירא Rav Zeira says
אזכה ואסק ואגמר לשמעתא מפומיה דמריה, Eska v'eiseik v'egmar l'shmaisa mipumei d'marei,
I should merit and go up to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
be able to learn this teaching from the one who taught it.
Because this is רב יצחק בר נחמני Rav Yitzchak bar Nachmani saying
in the name of רב אלעזר. Rav Elazar. רב אלעזר Rav Elazar
was in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So רב זירא Rav Zeira says
I look forward to the time I can go to רב אלעזר
Rav Elazar to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and learn this straight from
רב אלעזר. Rav Elazar. כי סליק, Ki salik, when he went to
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אשכח לרבי אלעזר, ashkach l'Rav Elazar, he found
רב אלעזר. Rav Elazar. אמר ליה אמרת הלכה כרבי יוסי בן כיפר?
Amar lei amarta halacha k'Rabbi Yose ben Kippar? Have you said the
הלכה halacha is like רבי יוסי בן כיפר Rabbi Yose ben Kippar
that really a month into the 20th year is sufficient?
Is that really how you פוסקין? paskin? So אמר ליה מסתברא אמרי,
amar lei mistavra amri, I said it makes sense that we rule
like him. Why? מדיכוליה פרקין תני יום אחד, Midekulo pirkin tani yom
echad,
since the whole I mean entire פרק perek. it says three and
a day, nine and a day, twelve and a day, thirteen and
a day. והכא לא תני, V'hacha lo tani, and here it didn't
say and a day. So it doesn't mean you have to be
20 and a day your 21st year. It means somewhere in your
20th year. שמע מינה מסתברא כוותיה, Shma mina mistavra k'vasai, so it
makes sense to go like him. It makes sense that the פשט
pshat of our משנה is not 20 and a day your 21st
year. It means into your 20th year. And since he says that
means a month in, it makes sense that that's the read of
our משנה and that that's the הלכה. halacha So הדרן עלך יוצא
דופן, Hadran lach Yotzei Dofen, so that is the end of that.
Now again what's important to note as I said is that in
our discussion here other than a hint about this aspect of יבום
Yibum, that it's like a קטן which again יבום Yibum. is very
much about the act of sex and about physical maturity. There's no
indication that this is really that he's still considered a minor. The
emphasis here is really that he is what do you call it?
That he is that he's not that he's not
whether he's considered fertile or not fertile or sterile for the laws
of יבום, it's very much in the context of יבום is the
whole discussion and not that in other הלכות halachos guy could be
20 years old or 34 years
old according to. So that's not so clear here at all, but
that is, but that is the הלכה halacha as developed elsewhere. So
that is the end of, you know, that פרק. perek We are
not done with those, the discussion about adulthood because again, it's a
very strange the way the פרקים prakim are divided. Because we have
all these משניות mishnayos about ages of maturity, but it started in
the middle of a פרק. perek. It didn't start at the beginning
of a פרק. And also it doesn't end at the end of
this פרק because the next משנה continues the discussion. So let's take
a look now at the next משנה.
Okay, so this anecdote is kind of subversive. In what way? In
the way that you can't really trust the oral מסורה mesorah unless
it goes directly from the person. And sure enough when he went
and and found the פסקא piska of the master, he found out
that the transmission was a little bit garbled.
Right, a little, right. It wasn't that he, he still made sense.
Yeah, but that's a good point, and that we do actually find
that a number of times
in the גמרא Gemara that when you know that it's clear that
sometimes they didn't get the message exactly straight. And you know, you're
right, sort of what is the, you know, on the surface of
it, it's just trying to sort of make clarify, look, here's what
the real הלכה Halacha is. But the fact that the גמרא Gemara
preserves the mistake and the correction and sort of leaves you with
understanding that sometimes there are those issues, you're right, I mean that
does, you know, you know, that does
raise profound questions. I'll just respond to that and say that, you
know,
why are there all the debates in the גמרא? Gemara Like where
do they come from? If you assume that it's all הלכה למשה
מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, like it's all מסורה mesorah and it's תורה
שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh and so on. So there's basically two
schools of thought. You know, there's one school that bases itself on
the משנה in עדיות, Eduyos, you know,
that says משעמדו תלמידי בית שמאי ובית הלל שלא שמשו כל צרכן,
mishe'amdu talmidei Beis Shammai u-Beis Hillel shelo shimshu kol tzarchan, you know,
when you had all these students that were not spending enough time
really completely immersed in their Rebbe's תורה, Torah, and they didn't get,
they didn't get the message 100 percent. It led to forgetfulness or
imprecision and that led to, you know, debate. And that's why the
debate occurred in the period of, you know, after, after שמאי and
הלל. And that it's basically based on forgetfulness and inaccuracy of transmission.
However, the רמב״ם Rambam really rejected that because that served as a
weapon for the Karaites to attack the Rabbinate, the Rabbanite or whatever
you call it, because they basically said, "Look, once you guys admit
that you have all these debates and these debates are evidence that
you didn't pass, that you know, that there was, as you said,
garbled transmission, so then how do we trust anything? So you guys
got the whole thing wrong, you know." So that was their basic
critique, to which the רמב״ם Rambam therefore was very important that he
said that, "No, no, no. Really, there's a tiny amount that's direct
transmission. That's what we call הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha lemoshe misinai. That's
like like point-one percent of our entire תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-be'al
peh. All the rest is just derived by the human intellect. And
you know, and therefore it's not about מסורה. mesorah. It's about human
derivation. If it's human derivation, there're going to be different conclusions."
What do you do with the משנה in עדיות Eduyos then?
Okay, so that's because they did not work enough to understand the
methods of the רבנים, Rabbanim, which would've led to similar conclusions. But
anyway, so that issue that you're raising is an important question about
how does acknowledging that there can be, you know, errors in transmission
have, you know, what does that do to our understanding of תורה
שבעל פה? Torah she-be'al peh? I guess once we're talking about that,
I'd like to say one other point which is also, what exactly
is the difference? You know, if you told me how do we
פסקן, pasken, I'd say, "Oh, we פסקן pasken this way." "How do
you know we פסקן pasken this way?" I say, "Because look, all
the, that's the way it makes sense based on the sources and
based on this." So how is him saying "No, I said it
makes sense" different than saying "I said the הלכה Halacha. was"? Which
raises a broader question of what does the גמרא Gemara ever mean
when it says הלכתא hilchasa X? How does it come to that
conclusion, הלכתא hilchasa X? You know, how does it know? So it
could very well be that הלכתא hilchasa often reflects the idea of
established practice, right? Like פוק חזי מאי עמא דבר puk chazi mai
ama davar and the way like what is the, you know, what
is the way people are acting. So it could be that sometimes
הלכתא hilchasa rather than sort of being like a judgment of how
we should rule based on the evidence might more be a reflection
of how people are actually פסקנינג. paskening. Like the גמרא Gemara in
סנהדרין Sanhedrin says about, indicates that that's an important factor in terms
of determining like what the פסק psak is and so on, about,
you know, about what סוגיא דעלמא sugya d'alma is, what sort of
the way people go on. So I think that's also very interesting
that the idea of הלכתא hilchasa is contrasted to what we would
normally consider to be classic פסק הלכה, psak halacha, which is you
look at the evidence and you make a reasoned judgment about what
the הלכה halakha is. So then there is no contradiction then?
He said he's not...
No, there is a contradiction! הלכתא Hilchasa means that that's the established
practice, and he said, "No, I didn't say הלכתא, hilchasa, I said
it makes sense to פסקן." pasken.
So he didn't answer the question.
He did answer the question! There was a, there was a mis-transmission.
No, no, meaning like he's saying it makes sense to פסקן pasken
but
he's saying but we don't? No, I don't mean we don't, but
it's not that I'm claiming that that's the established פסק. psak. I'm
just saying that that's what, that's the פסק psak that makes sense.
But that raises the question of what else does הלכתא hilchasa mean
if not this is how it makes sense to פסקן? pasken? And
it might mean that this is the פסק psak that's been established
as practice.
Okay, so assumption that הלכתא hilchasa is a received tradition.
It's pretty funny if it's received tradition if you often have debates,
you know, you have גמרא... Gemara that everybody is debating and the
last line, received tradition.
But this is the one that, that is, as it has developed.
Oh you mean, oh you mean somebody at some stage after all
of these there developed a consensus and now we've received it. So
you're saying the same, it's a consensus, but rather than a consensus
of practice, you're saying a consensus of פסק, psak, that proceeds. Okay,
recognize it. Alright, now let's take a look at the גמרא, the
next פרק. בא סימן התחתון עד שלא בא העליון. Ba Siman Hatachton
Ad Shelo Ba Haelyon. So the last penultimate משנה that you did
on שבת Shabbos was about the signs of physical maturity by a
by a young girl when she's when she's considered to be a
נערה Na'arah, and then also a בוגרת. Bogeres, So, actually it's interesting
because the משנה
listed different signs, listed signs of when she was a בוגרת, but
the גמרא talks about other physical signs of maturity that תוספות says
were signs that she was a נערה, Na'arah that she, that proved
that she had pubic hair. This משנה clearly is talking about certain
types of upper signs, meaning of developments of the breast that would
indicate that she has pubic hairs, that would become at the same
time we would expect her to be a נערה Na'arah to get
the two pubic hairs. בא סימן התחתון עד שלא בא העליון. Ba
Siman Hatachton Ad Shelo Ba Haelyon. If she has the upper signs
without yet the lower ones, without yet the pubic hairs, is she
a נערה Na'arah, or not? So the הלכה halakha is אוכלת או
מתייבמת. Ocheles O Misjabemes. She can she can either do חליצה or
יבום, means she's an adult. Yes, the signs of physical maturity in
the breast development is just as good as the pubic hairs, she's
a נערה, naarah she's an adult. I'm sorry,
I misread it. I misread it. I jumped to the second case.
I'm sorry. Okay. בא לתחתון, Ba Letachton, I the second, this is
the more interesting one. בא סימן התחתון עד שלא בא העליון. Ba
Siman Hatachton Ad Shelo Ba Haelyon. She has the pubic hairs without
the upper development, without the breast development. Then everybody agrees that's an
adult. אוכלת או מתייבמת, Ocheles O Misjabemes, that's an adult, the pubic
hairs
and she's twelve years old. בא עליון עד שלא בא התחתון. Ba
Elyon Ad Shelo Ba Hatachton. If she has the upper signs of
development without the lower ones, אף על פי שאי אפשר, Af Al
Pi She'ee Efshar, even though it's impossible, it will never happen. רבי
מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir Omer לא חולצת ולא מתייבמת.
So I'm sorry, she's still a minor if she doesn't have the
pubic hairs and she can't do חליצה or יבום. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim
Omrim אוכלת או מתייבמת. Ocheles O Misjabemes. No she could do חליצה
or יבום. Why? מפני שאמרו Mipnei She'amru אפשר לתחתון לבוא עד שלא
בא העליון. Efshar Latachton Lavo Ad Shelo Ba Haelyon.
It's possible to get the lower pubic hairs without the upper development,
אבל אי אפשר לעליון לבוא עד שלא בא התחתון. Aval Ee Efshar
Le'elyon Lavo Ad Shelo Ba Hatachton. But you cannot get the upper
development, the breast development that is of significance, and actually I was
checking on this last night on Wikipedia, someone actually told me over
שבת Shabbos I was talking about this, that there's something called the
Tanner, T-A-N-N-E-R, stages of development, you can look it up on Wikipedia
on the web, and you actually see a very, almost like the
משנה that we did on שבת, Shabbos, very specific listing of the
pubic development and breast development at different stages, and you'll notice at
one, I think it's stage three comes right around the age of
twelve to twelve and a half and right exactly at this time.
So anyway, so actually the breasts begin to show some development before
the pubic hairs, but the stage of development that's significant, says this
משנה, that will not happen unless there's also pubic hairs. And therefore
if she has the upper development and she does not have the
pubic hairs, she's an adult, we assume the pubic hairs came and
they fell out because it's impossible that you would have that development
without also being with the pubic hairs. אבל אי אפשר לעליון לבוא
עד שלא בא התחתון. Aval Ee Efshar Le'elyon Lavo Ad Shelo Ba
Hatachton. You cannot have the upper without the lower and therefore if
even if all you see is the upper, you assume that she
has had the pubic hairs and she is an adult. What?
No, saying that, that's רב שמעון בן יוחאי, Rav Shimon Bar Yochai,
that סימנים שנתנו חכמים מלמטה למעלה. Simanim Shenasnu Chachamim Milmata L'mala. Right.
So the question is what's the relationship. Right. So everybody agrees by
the way that that the pubic hair is what is significant. The
question is what can you infer about the pubic hair from the
breast development. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says nothing, just go by what
you see and the pubic hair, and the חכמים Chachamim say no,
if you have the upper development you can assume the lower. So
now the גמרא says אף על פי שאי אפשר. Af Al Pi
She'ee Efshar. So it says if you have the upper without the
lower, even though it's impossible. Even though it's impossible? והלא בא? V'ha
Lo Ba? What do you mean? That's exactly what we said, you
have the upper without the lower even though it's impossible. So the
גמרא says בא לרבי מאיר. Ba L'Rabbi Meir. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir who says it is possible. So according to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that's what you're seeing, the upper development without the
lower. But it has to make a point, אף על פי שאי
אפשר לרבנן. Af Al Pi She'ee Efshar L'Rabbanan. So it says you
have the upper without the lower, then saying in parenthesis, the Rabbis
will say that that's impossible, as we're about to see they're going
to say if you had the upper you had to have the
lower, but רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir thinks it is possible, so therefore
according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, she's still a minor. So the
גמרא says וליתני בא העליון רבי מאיר אומר לא חולצת ולא יבמה
באמת וחכמים אוכלת או מתייבמת. V'lisni Ba Haelyon Rabbi Meir Omer Lo
Choletzes V'lo Yesama Be'emes Vachachamim Ocheles O Misjabemes. So why do you
have to say possible, impossible? Just tell me the הלכה. halakha If
you have the upper development without the lower one, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says she's a minor, can't do חליצה יבום, and the חכמים
Chachamim say she's an adult, she can do חליצה יבום. ואנא ידענא,
V'ana Yadana, I would have known משום דאי אפשר הוא, Mishum D'ee
Efshar Hu,
because why did the Rabbis say that the upper is an upper?
Because they assume the upper is a proof, it's impossible without the
lower. No,
I couldn't just have said that. I had to explain what it's
about. Why did I have to explain what it's about? אילו תנא
אף על פי שאי אפשר, Ilu Tanna Af Al Pi She'ee Efshar,
if you had not had that phrase, even though it's impossible, meaning
that that phrase underscores that the... reason the rabbis say upper development
counts is because it proves lower development. If you did not have
that phrase, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have thought רוב נשים
תחתון אתי ברישא ומיעוט עליון אתי ברישא. rov nashim tachton ati beresha
u'miut elyon ati beresha.
Most women, first they get the pubic hairs and then the upper
development. But there are some that it's the reverse. Okay, so this
woman has the upper development and not the lower. So maybe she's
of this minority of women that get the upper development before the
lower. So רבי מאיר לטעמיה דחייש למיעוטא. Rabbi Meir letamei dechaish lemiuta.
So Rabbi Meir goes according to his reasoning. He's concerned that she's
of this, you know, five percent of the population that have the
upper development without the lower and she's still a minor and that's
why he says he's a minor because maybe she's of this five
percent of the population. ורבנן לטעמייהו דלא חיישי למיעוטא. Verabanan letameihu dela
chaishi lemiuta. The rabbis go according to the reasoning, we don't assume
she's part of the five percent of the population, we assume she's
part of the ninety-five and the presence of the breast development is
proof that there was the pubic hair. So it's the same debate,
except it's not אי אפשר. ee efshar. They're not saying it never
happens. They're just saying that it's, you know, we're not going to
be concerned about the tiny percentages of cases where it might happen.
So now why does that matter? That we're not that it's about
not never but about not being concerned about a small percentage? Because
then we would have limited the debate and here's what we would
have said. והני מילי בסתמא, Vehani mili bistama,
that's when you didn't bother checking for the pubic hair, you just
saw the upper development. So you just saw the upper. Rabbi Meir
says, I'm not convinced yet, there's still a small percentage. ורבנן אמרי,
Verabanan amri, that's pretty good evidence, she's probably of the ninety-five percent
and the upper development is a good enough of a proof. אבל
היכא דבדקו ולא אשתכח, Aval heicha de'badku velo ishtakach, but I would
have said if you took the next step and you checked for
the pubic hairs and you didn't see it, so you have direct
evidence of the absence of pubic hairs, אימא מודי ליה רבנן. eima
modi leh rabanan. Now the rabbis would say, "Oh, there's no pubic
hairs, now you're right, now we see she's part of the five
percent." And maybe they would actually admit that if there's no pubic
hairs, you consider her to be a minor because they're not saying
it's impossible, they're just saying it's five percent. מודי ליה לרבי מאיר
דעליון קדים. modi leh leRabbi Meir de'elyon kadim.
You see this was part of the five percent that the upper
development happened first. קא משמע לן דאי אפשר. Ka mashma lan de'ee
efshar. That's why the Mishnah has to tell you, the rabbis are
not saying it's five percent, they're saying it's zero percent, that it's
impossible, the upper development without the lower.
I still don't need to say אף על פי שאי אפשר af
al pi she'ee efshar because you've just done... I understand. Because you
say the reason later anyway. I understand.
The Gemara
will discuss that a little later. So ודאי אתו, vadai atu, they
must have come ומהדר הוא דנתור, umahadar hu denatur, and they fell
out. So by saying it's impossible, we actually is a relevant halakhah
to tell you that even with direct observation, we go by our
by what we know, not by what we see, and we say
that they must have fallen out and she's an adult. Now the
Gemara says, בשלמא לרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב שדים נכונו ושערך צמח. Bishlama
leRabbi Meir hainu dechtiv shadayim nakhonu use'arekh tzimach. Oh,
so now we have some pesukim that come from the Haggadah, actually
they come from יחזקאל, Yechezkel, but okay. It makes sense according to
Rabbi Meir, that's what the פסוק pasuk says when it describes the
development of this young girl in in יחזקאל Yechezkel that, you know,
is used as a metaphor for the for the redemption, for being
ready for redemption, that the breasts were ready and the and the
hair had sprouted forth. So it sounds like that's the order. First
the breasts develop and then the pubic hair. אלא לרבנן איפכא מיבעי
ליה, Ela lerabanan ipcha mibaei leh, according to the rabbis it had
to be the reverse. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is what the
פסוק pasuk means: כיון ששדים נכונו, Keivan sheshadayim nakhonu, once the breasts
set to develop, ידוע ששערך צמח, yadua shese'arekh tzimach, you know that
the hair has sprouted forth. Okay, בשלמא לרבי מאיר. bishlama leRabbi Meir.
By the way, it all depends on what you mean, like how
are you defining, you know, what degree of development of the breasts,
what degree of development of the pubic hair, so you can go
look at the web and you can sort of see how some
in some ways you could say the the breasts come, you know,
develop first and in some way the hair developed first. Anyway, בשלמא
לרבי מאיר היינו דכתיב ועשות מצרים דדיך למען שדי נעוריך, Bishlama leRabbi
Meir hainu dechtiv ve'asot Mitzrayim dadayich lemaan shadei neurayich,
when מצרים, Mitzrayim, this is sort of being critical about how בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael allowed themselves to be abused by the Egyptians, so
it's sort of talking about like a metaphor of like, you know,
sexual abuse when מצרים Mitzrayim sort of, you know, sort of
manhandled, smashed your your breasts in order that you should. Now the
word שדי shadei could be שדים, shadayim, which is breasts, which is
how we'll read it in a minute, but here they're reading more
like the Aramaic word like to cast forth, that you cast forth
your youth, which means that it's sort of like your hair, you
know, your pubic hair came out. So it again seems that it
talks first about the breasts and then the pubic
hair. אלא
לרבנן איפכא מיבעי ליה,
Ela lerabanan
ipcha mibaei leh, according
to the rabbis the order should have been
the opposite. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is what it means: כיון
שבאו דדיך, Keivan sheba'u dadayich, once your breasts had come, ידוע שבאו
נעוריך. yadua sheba'u neurayich. It was proof that you had already been
a נערה and that the pubic hair had already come prior to
that. ואי בעית אימא מה שדי כולה בדדי כתיב. Ve'ee bayit eima
ma shadei kula bedadai ktiv. שדי shadei does not mean to cast
forth your youth, that your youth had already arrived or arrived afterwards,
but it means the word again from the word שדים, shadayim, breasts.
והכי קאמר קודשא בריך הוא לישראל, Vehachi ka'amar Kudsha Brich Hu leYisrael,
this is what God is saying to Israel: אימת דדדיך לא חזרת.
eimat dedadayich lo hazart.
So when your breasts began to develop, you did not do תשובה,
teshuvah, or רשי Rashi says another interpretation is when they began to
sort of.
Manhandle your breasts you did not do תשובה teshuva with the meaning
again using this whole metaphor but when they mistreated you, אשתדו דדייך
נמי לא חזרת. Ishtadu dadayich nami lo hazarta.
And when they continued to develop or רש"י says or when they
actually completely
withered you still did not do תשובה. teshuva. So it's a metaphor
for how בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael suffered at the hands of מצרים
Mitzrayim and did not do תשובה. teshuva. But anyway, both of them
are talking about the breasts and not about
the pubic hair. Okay. דכולי עלמא מיהא תתא סמכינן. Dekhulei alma miha
tata samkhinan.
Now what's clear as I pointed out the משנה is everybody agrees
that the סימן siman that matters is the pubic hair. The only
question is, is the breasts evidence of the pubic hair or not?
The rabbis say yes and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says not necessarily.
So מנלן, Menalan, where do you know that? It's clear that the
גמרא takes it for granted as Michael said, so much of this
is not in the פסוקים, psukim, but it's clear that if we're
talking about adulthood we go by physical development and that's the גמרא
takes it for granted and therefore but how do you know but
girls do have both the pubic hair and the development of the
breasts. By the way that's considered secondary characteristics right when they talk
about puberty right when they talk about the development they talk the
primary is basically just the genital area right? The breast is considered
secondary right?
There's something so voyeuristic it just feels...
yeah I was waiting for that I was waiting for that comment.
So here's the question I want to ask again Rivka is that
if you go ahead and like I did last night and you
type in Tanner stages of development when you see all these medical
pictures which are describing exactly this breasts and pubic hair and this
stage and that stage and what does it develop it doesn't feel
voyeuristic right? So here it feels voyeuristic why? Because here
if you don't have diagrams if you're dealing with words
and knowing that these rabbis they're not
asking but
they're interested in the same thing. But they have to decide halakhic
decisions and at
what age and that's okay.
I think the real problem is not that they I will tell
you right well although for some הלכות halakhot you do care for
דאורייתא de'oraita you do care for the pubic hairs and so on
but why is that? Yeah I mean you could sort of ask
like by a lot of הלכה
why are some things I mean there're different criteria on which you
I mean just because it would have been more pleasant like less
discomforting I think the real question is not that they care about
physical development I think the problem is that when you look at
a medical text it's an anonymous voice and it therefore even if
it was written by men which could be critiqued also at least
it's not it doesn't feel voyeuristic because you're reading something in a
very anonymous voice and here you're hearing it through the mouth of
male rabbis and I think that's makes it more difficult. I don't
think it's the fact that they're actually talking about it.
Absolutely male rabbis and if they're are
they obsessed with this wouldn't they be obsessed with any הלכה question?
No.
We could do a statistical analysis to see I don't think they
have a disproportionate amount of discussion about this.
What's very interesting is people seem to naturally early on and say
oh why don't you just say just check you don't have to
deal with any of this.
Well okay so we're going to get wait till a minute because
talk about the real question is do you who checks men or
women? Okay so we're going to get there. So let's keep on
going. All right.
Yeah
it seems a little odd that no one has mentioned
menstruation for women as a...
Aha that's interesting I wonder if that's tied to that's a good
point I wonder if that's tied to the fact that we also
have a הלכה that one day old could be considered a נדה.
niddah. So if you say one day old could be considered a
נדה niddah then do you want to link those two in that
way? So you need some combination why don't you say twelve years
and the onset of rather than twelve years and pubic hair? Right
that's interesting yeah. I don't know. So let's take a look.
How do we know about the male?
Right because there's no counterpart. That's true. That's a good point that's
a good point too. Right because that would be then much younger
if you went by the ejaculation or something or at least the
potential for that. Okay דכולי עלמא מיהא תתא סמכינן. Dekhulei alma miha
tata samkhinan. We rely on the lower sign on the pubic hair.
מנלן Menalan where do you know that? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל אמר קרא. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
vekhen tana devei Rabbi Yishmael amar kra. The פסוק pasuk says איש
או אשה כי יעשו מכל חטאת האדם ish o isha ki ya'asu
mikol hatot ha'adam a man or woman that does any of the
sins. Very important פסוק pasuk about the universal application of the law
at least for the prohibitions. השוה הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל עונשים שבתורה.
Hishva hakatuv isha le'ish lekhol onshim shebatorah. Woman is
compared to man for all the punishments all the prohibitions in the
Torah. מה איש Ma ish so therefore similar the question about when
you're considered an adult מה איש בסימן אחד אף אשה בסימן אחד.
Ma ish besiman echad af isha besiman echad. The same way a
man goes by one of the one sign pubic hair a woman
also goes by one sign. Because there's only that's the only clear
sign on the man. I mean there are other secondary but they're
not nearly as obvious as the secondary characteristics by woman so clearly
if you're going to go by a sign it will only be
the pubic hair. I understand but it's not as evident as by
the woman and it's also not as staged at the right place
same time as what we would say the onset of puberty. ואימא
או האי או האי. Ve'eima o hai o hai. Fine one doesn't
you don't need two but maybe it could be either one either
the pubic hair or the breast development. כאיש Ke'ish like a man.
מה איש תתא ולא עילא. Ma ish tata velo eila. The same
way by man you only go by the pubic hair אף because
as we just discussed that's really the only significant indicator אף אשה
תתא ולא עילא. Similarly by a woman. תניא נמי הכי. Tanya nami
hakhi. We taught similarly. אמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק כך היו מפרישין
Amar Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok kakh hayu mafrishin מפרשין ביבנה ואמרו mefarshin
be-Yavne ve-amru this is how they would explain in Yavne and they
said כל שבחתחתון שוב אין משגיחין על העליון. kol sheba-tachton shuv ein
mashgichin al ha-elyon. When you have the lower you don't care anymore
about the upper, the lower is indicative. Now and
presumably it means the upper is not significant or maybe it means
the upper at most is significant as an indicator of the of
the lower. תניא Tanya taught a Braita. רבן גמליאל אומר Rabban Gamliel
omer בנות כרכים benot krachim
now we get to talking about speculating or whatever observing and speculating.
So the
young girls in the cities תחתון ממהר לבוא tachton mmaher lavo the
pubic hair develops sooner מפני שרגילות במרחצאות mipnei sheragilot be-merchatza'ot
because they go into all these bathhouses and that somehow presumably stimulates
their body more and the development of the hair. בנות כפרים benot
kfarim
the young girls of the villages עליון ממהר לבוא elyon mmaher lavo
the upper develops more מפני שטוחנות בריחיים mipnei shetochanot bereichayim they grind
with the millstone and that develops their upper body more.
Where'd he get this information?
Was he walking around checking? Either he was checking or it was
apocryphal you know or it was something that he thought he observed
and he speculated right we have no idea. I understand I I
was awaiting for that right. I think this I think this is
more is more disturbing than the previous discussion. The previous discussion was
halakhic and you did not get the sense that they were directly
looking at the girls around them okay but this whole
thing is disturbing the intense pub- right the male
focus on the female body. Right I mean if you were here
yesterday you don't feel that way
I mean if you were here yesterday
you would have heard about how שמואל basically
had his young maidservants stand naked in front of him so he
could inspect them and and then he compensated them for the embarrassment
but he still made them do it so that basically... Right I
mean it's the term it's a the...
But the
women the same women determine if they're נדה nidda so the women
could check I don't know.
Okay well we're gonna get
to who checks but they're all they're constantly examining for blood they
can examine for hair.
I understand so we're going to get to who does the examining
in a minute we won't get to it today because we have
to wrap this up but it'll be first thing tomorrow so let's
just do three more lines and then we'll wrap up for today
okay. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer בנות
עשירים benot ashirim צד ימין ממהר לבוא tzad yamin mmaher lavo okay
exactly so
daughters from wealthy families the right side I presumably of the breast
develops quicker why שנושפות אפקיסטותיהן shenoshfot afkistoteihen
because it sort of bangs against they wear some type of jewelry
or a scarf on their right side and it stimulates it and
it bangs against it. בנות עניים benot aniyim צד שמאל ממהר לבוא
tzad smol mmaher lavo poor girls it develops more on the left
first מפני ששואבות כדי מים עליהן. mipnei shesho'avot kadei mayim aleihen. He
knows this he's noticed this it's not... Right I understand this is
their speculation this
is no halakhic implication whatsoever.
Exactly which is I think why it's more disturbing because it's not
halakhically significant at all. Right okay right because they carry the right
that they carry the the water. ואיבעית אימא Ve'iba'it eima מפני שנושאות
אחיהן על גיסיסיהן mipnei shenos'ot acheihen al gisisieihen because again the poor
girls they don't have servants or whatever they have to carry their
younger brothers and for whatever reason they carry it on their left
side and that leads to that.
So you agree this
shows a- this is definitely disturbing yes an irrelevant
focus on yes on girls on young girls right and their physical
development right.
I mean these were also at this time probably marriageable girls so...
Well they were marriageable since eight.
I understand. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan last
thing
last thing and then we will discuss who does the tracking tomorrow
so צד שמאל קודם לצד ימין tzad smol kodem letzad yamin so
here we go we're not distinguishing rich and poor left develops before
the right. רבי חנינא בן אחי רבי יהושע אומר Rabbi Chanina ben
achi Rabbi Yehoshua omer מעולם Me'olam here's a good point to end
on לא קדם צד שמאל לצד ימין lo kadam tzad smol letzad
yamin I've never seen the left breast develop before the right חוץ
מאחת שהיתה בשכונתי chutz me'achat shehayta bishchunati except for one girl that
was in my village שקדם צד שמאל לצד ימין shekadam tzad smol
letzad yamin that it developed first וחזרה ותנובה vechazra vetenava but presumably
in the end the right side caught up and that is where
we will end today.